<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-03-08T09:53:00-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>From the Roaring Twenties until the Depression</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/Roaring-twenties/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/Roaring-twenties/</id>
    <published>2015-03-08T09:53:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-04-18T14:47:33-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1 id="from-the-roaring-twenties-until-the-depression-sup1footnote1sup"&gt;From the Roaring Twenties until the Depression &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1920's saw attempts by the African Americans in Albuquerque to move their community forward and attempts by some whites to constrain them. As an example there was St. Timothy Richards. He accompanied his father Reverend Allen Richards who accepted the pastorate of Mt. Olive Baptist Church in 1912. S.T. had been trained and worked briefly as a teacher in his native Arkansas.  He could not practice that profession due to the racial discrimination of the public school system. He worked as a porter for a men's store eventually rising to the position of clerk there. In 1919 he became a railroad porter but that job would neither define nor contain him. He opened a grocery store in 1921 while still working as a railroad porter. He later sold the grocery and built a two story building on Marquette Avenue and Broadway that became important for the black community.  The first floor housed several restaurants, a night club, and a funeral home own by black entrepreneurs.  The top floor served for several years a black meeting space, the People's Hall, the first such public building for blacks in Albuquerque. Seniors interviewed in the 1970's remembered it as "a place where we could go and have socials," and "an exciting place for teenage people to go.  From high school we'd go down there at noon and have lunch." Richards also built the Ideal Hotel to serve as a public lodging facility for blacks when there weren't many other options for African Americans visiting Albuquerque. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second example was Silas W. Henry who is first listed in the 1910 city directory as a bootblack but by 1913 had become a partner in the Bryant Messenger Service. He left that after a year and started a string of his own businesses from a parcel delivery service in 1915 to his own messenger service and transfer companies by 1921. In 1922 he started the Henry Printing Company and began publishing a newspaper the Southwest Review.  This was not the first black newspaper in Albuquerque. A black lawyer named Oscar Hudson had similarly started a printing service and newspaper called the New Age in 1913 but it only lasted a year. The paper's short lifespan clearly indicated that the first newspaper found little success with the black community of the time and no copies of it have been found extant. The situation was different when Henry founded the Southwest Review.  He had the wherewithal and financial standing to maintain the newspaper even though the black community had not grown that much. The newspaper started in 1922 and lasted until Henry's illness and subsequent death in 1927. The newspaper's front page was usually based on the national NAACP news service and wrote about national issues affecting African Americans.  It also had regular articles and notices about local events both in Albuquerque and in other New Mexican black communities in places like Las Cruces, Roswell and Vado. It tried to be a regional paper with an office and a reporter in El Paso, Texas as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Southwester Plaindealer" src="/images/SWPlaindealer.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1924 a competing black newspaper called the Southwestern Plaindealer was founded by our friend S.T. Richards. We know of this only because he sent a letter and a copy to the governor of New Mexico Arthur T. Hannett.  The note requested that Hannett appoint African Americans to some state offices as none had been appointed before.  The issue of the newspaper had an article praising Hannett and urged African Americans to support the Democratic Party as a party of reform and "clean' politics in contrast to the Republican Party which they had traditionally supported since Lincoln. It was in clear contrast to the other black newspaper S.W. Henry's Southwest Review which was staunchly Republican.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both black newspapers and the Albuquerque African American community itself were shaken by the state legislature's passage of a law that allowed the segregation of African Americans, and only African Americans, in separate schools if local school boards so wanted. Although some segregation had been practiced in New Albuquerque since its origins in 1880, the African American population had been able to rebuff segregation in the local schools and proposed segregation on the street cars. The local NAACP had been formed in 1913 to lead these fights. By the 1920's although some establishments still refused to serve African Americans and the theaters had a separate balcony area for blacks, there was only limited segregation in public facilities in Albuquerque. The state legislature's allowance of segregated schools was received as quite a blow to the black community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The change allowing segregated schools came in an omnibus bill in the state legislature reforming the school code that had been passed in 1923. In 1925 a state legislature more concerned with establishing a new way to finance schools, regulate school boards, depoliticize school board elections, and change teacher compensation, passed Senate Bill 95 which also contained an amendment to allow local school boards to set up separate schools for African Americans.  The new law said If the county or municipal school board and the state board of education:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is for the best advantage and interest of the school that separate room be provided for the teaching of pupils [of] African descent and such rooms are so provided, such pupils may not be admitted to school rooms occupied and used by pupils of Caucasian or other descent.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill passed the state House of Representatives with only one dissenting vote. The Albuquerque NAACP sent a delegation that met with the state senate's steering committee.  Despite this the measure passed the state senate overwhelmingly (42-3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right of New Mexicans of  Latino descent not to be forced to attend schools separate from whites had been guaranteed by the New Mexico state Constitution in 1912. Despite this a state legislature dominated by Republicans and a Democratic governor allowed a "Jim Crow" change in the school code thus ignoring the interests of New Mexico African Americans. New Mexican African Americans were politically impotent and could not affect their statewide fate when the forces of racism prevailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a last ditch effort to prevent the governor from signing the bill into law, the Albuquerque NAACP organized a petition. The petititon read in part:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The State of New Mexico has never been a Jim Crow state heretofore and we feel that this measure is only the beginning of segregation and disenfranchisement of the Negro in our state.  We pray you will not sanction a law that will prohibit or hinder the educational progress of any citizens regardless of race, color or religion, as such a measure as the Bill above referred to would certainly do, by adding your signature…&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The governor ignored the petition of 41 people and signed the bill anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The news hit the Albuquerque black community like a thunderbolt. There had been little racial discrimination in Albuquerque and the black community felt it had escaped the racism mores of the south with their racism and segregation. The overwhelming passage of this law allowing segregation pointed out the precariousness of their position.  Almost every legislator, no matter the political party, was willing to sacrifice the interests of black schoolchildren in order to get a new school code that put school systems on a firmer financial and organizational footing. More to the point the racism of the Southern states was making inroads into New Mexico.  New Mexico had never been totally free of prejudice but the black community of New Mexico had convinced itself that things were better there than other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No issues of S.T. Richards' Southwestern Plaindealer survive from that time, but S.W. Henry's Southwest Review trumpeted its opposition loud and clear:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[the bill] brought out a test tht will long be remembered by colored New Mexicans as to who to trust as friends. [S.W. Henry blames] Ilfeld of Las Vegas a JEW, - Holt of Las Cruces, a staunch republican (?) whose majority was made sure by Negro votes of Dona Ana County, - Espinosa, a Mexican American of Belen and others of the ‘do anything-you-say boss type' must be put down as the vilest enemies of the Negro race.  They just simply hate Negroes and Negroes know it. They supported this measure because of their own personal feeling and prejudices. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reporting on the next NAACP meeting the paper said the "colored citizens were bitter in their denunciation of the legislature," and "that many are discouraged and are preparing to leave the state." The paper said that some had already left. The paper was bitter too and in an article otherwise favorable about the adoption of a state flag said ‘ …it is too bad that at the same session …[that African Americans] are now by the growth of race prejudice discriminated against by law as if they are lepers.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote7"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;"  In the March 28, 1925 issue the paper quoted State Senator Holt of Las Cruces as saying to a protesting delegation of African Americans, "Law or no law we are going to have separate schools." In an editorial in the same issue the paper lamented that the Republican state senate was hypocritical and did not live up to its Republican principles. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote8"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry's Southwest Review continued to publish until 1927 when Henry's illness and subsequent death ended its run. In fact only the school boards in the southern part of the state like Las Cruces and in the southeastern part of the state colloquially called "Little Texas" because of its large population of Texas immigrants and its proximity to Texas, organized separate schools for blacks. It has been reported that an official of the Albuquerque school board offered the town's African Americans their own school in the late 1930's, but they were turned down.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote9"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  In Catherine Watkins Duncan's 1938 master's thesis she lists nine separate elementary schools that were set up in the southern and southeastern New Mexico locales.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote10"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  None of the schools in Albuquerque were segregated and no separate schools for African Americans were set up there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great exodus of African Americans from New Mexico that Henry had predicted did not happen. If we subtract the soldiers anomalously posted down near the Mexico border  the 1920 New Mexico black population is approximately 2133. By the end of the 1920's in the 1930 census the number of African Americans in New Mexico had grown to 2850, an increase of about 33%. Albuquerque's black population had increased to over 400 thus doubling after two decades of stagnation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we group people into the same four age groups as before, children (&amp;lt;15), young adults (15 to 34), mature adults (35 to 64) and elders (65+), we can see how the population had changed. In 1930 much more of the black population is comprised of children and there is a greater share of mature adults.  There is a smaller proportion of young adults and of elders in the 1930 population. It is significant that most of these children (58%) were born in New Mexico. Even if we restrict our analysis to children who weren't in the 1920 census 45% were born in New Mexico. Of the children born since the 1920 manuscript census over 79% were born in New Mexico. Although only 12% of the people listed in the 1920 manuscript census were also listed in the 1930 manuscript census, the increase in population is made up not only of new immigrants but of an increasing number of children within the stable core of Albuquerque's black population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Chart of Age Roups in 1920 and 1930" src="/images/Chart3a.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 1930 therefore we can see that since the 1920's there is beginning to be a growing group of African Americans who would consider Albuquerque the place to put down roots, to start and to rear a family. This group augmented the small group of African Americans who had been settled in Albuquerque during the 1900 to 1920 period. This core was not only enough to produce the beginnings and growing maturity of African American social institutions and groups, it was enough to frighten whites and cause defensive measures to ensure white dominance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was in the 1920's that we began to see deeds and real estate contracts with racially restrictive covenants that banned whites in some areas from selling to African Americans. The November 28, 1925 issue of the Southwest Review has a main headline and front page story about a court case concerning Albuquerque housing discrimination. Eugenia Keleher sued in district court to prevent Charles Zapf, an Albuquerque realtor, from selling building lots to "persons of African blood or descent." There had been a "gentleman's agreement," an unwritten rule, against such a sale that Zapf threatened to break.  Keleher was suing to have the warrant deed to the lots changed to include the discriminatory stipulation. This move to formalize the informal housing discrimination system by having the legal system enforce it was a major change. The prominence that the newspaper gives this news argues for the rarity of such Albuquerque racial discrimination being made public by having the legal system enforce it.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote11"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Several such racially restrictive covenants were written into Albuquerque deeds for the rest of the 1920's and beyond.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote12"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was an avalanche of these racially restrictive covenants in Northern, Midwestern, and Far Western urban areas around the county at that time. Some historians have linked the appearance of these covenants to two Supreme Court decisions.  In a case brought to the Supreme Court by the NAACP and its allies, Buchanan v. Warely, the Supreme Court ruled that it was illegal for a municipal government to racially zone an area. In contrast the Supreme Court ruled in 1926 that private contracts that contained racially restrictive covenants were legal in Corrigan v. Buckley. Later historians have challenged that explanation saying that racial covenants predate the 1917 decision, they did not occur first and often in those places whose municipal zoning was struck down, and that those explanations are too simplistic for what was a more complex process.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote13"&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One later historian has attributed the rise in restrictive covenants to a multistage process. In the first stage the wave of race riots, that is, white attacks upon African Americans and their communities that occurred from 1917 to 1921 led some to view segregation as the way to prevent social violence in urban areas. In the second stage institutions developed to pursue the segregationist course of action.  He mentions the National Association of Real Estates Boards who through their policy recommendations and manuals spread the idea of racial covenants to realtors throughout the country. Once the federal government also practiced these racially restrictive policies in the New Deal programs that sprang up in the 1930's, the institutionalization of racial covenants was underway. Although the Supreme Court ruled that enforcement of such bans by state or local authorities was illegal in 1948, racially restrictive covenants continued until local conditions or the 1965 Fair Housing Act made them illegal.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote14"&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albuquerque did not experience any race riots or racial violence at all. The riot closest to Albuquerque was the 1921 Tulsa race riot and that was over 600 miles away. The National Association of Real Estate Boards probably did have some contact either formal or informal with local realtors and as we shall see in later chapters the New Deal agencies were certainly active in Albuquerque. Those areas of New Mexico in which school segregation appeared were areas where the black population was increasing. Although the total African American population of New Mexico had only increased 33% from 1920 to 1930 some places increased more than others. The total number of African Americans in Las Cruces, as an example of a place which created segregated schools, saw an increase of its population from 54 in 1920 to 206 in 1930 some 382%. Another such place Clovis, New Mexico saw its African American population increase 283% in the same period. In Albuquerque the African American population almost doubled and as we have seen they became more interested in owning property and raising families. Any real explanation of the perceived need for whites to get a better legal support for discrimination and segregation will probably be complex, nuanced and multifaceted. However one of those facets will be a perceived growth in the African American population and the change to a more settled African American community which threatened the white monopolization of schools and residential areas.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>From 1900 to 1920</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/from-1900-to-1920/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/from-1900-to-1920/</id>
    <published>2015-03-07T21:01:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2015-04-18T14:46:13-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1 id="from-1900-to-1920"&gt;From 1900 to 1920&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning in 1900 we can see from Figure 1 that the percentage of New Mexico's black population who lived in Albuquerque (the darker line) fluctuated in a narrow range from 10% to 15%. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  At all points from 1900 to 1940 the percentage of New Mexican African Americans who lived in Albuquerque was greater than the percentage of the total population of New Mexico who lived in Albuquerque (the lighter line) according to the census.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Chart Percentages of African Americans" src="/images/Chart1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 1900 on Albuquerque is the city with the largest black population although the town with the second largest black population varies over time. The demographics of Albuquerque therefore reveal the contours of African American urban life in New Mexico. Demographic statistics can be helpful as long as we remember that they only give a snapshot and an approximate look at the community. Their numbers give a false impression of precision and accuracy. As long as one remembers we are dealing with people rather than numbers and that the numbers themselves represent fickle data collection at best, demographics can be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1900 New Mexico was a predominantly rural place. It was still a United States controlled territory rather than a state. Eighty-six % of the inhabitants lived in rural areas as defined by the U.S. Census bureau and only fourteen percent lived in urban areas. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; New Mexican African Americans were a much more urban group with 35% living in urban areas, but even this meant 65% were living in rural areas. Of the New Mexican black urban dwellers 40% lived in Albuquerque. They lived in a community quite different from other New Mexico African American communities. In New Mexico as a whole African American men outnumbered African American women 1023 to 587.  Even in urban areas there were 105 African American men for each 100 African American women. In 1900 Albuquerque there were equal numbers of black men and black women in total but among black adults the ratio was 110 black males for every 100 black females.  There were only slightly more single males in Albuquerque than married ones while in the New Mexico territory as a whole single black males outnumbered married ones by a wide margin. Even so black women who lived in Albuquerque were much more likely to be married (54.5% of black women) than black women in the territory as a whole (43% of black women.) There was also an abnormal number of widows among black women.  The territorial figure was high at 12% of black women but in Albuquerque it was more than twice that at 25%. A larger proportion of black women were widows than were otherwise unmarried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The black community in turn of the twentieth century Albuquerque had all the attributes of a recently settled community. Over a third of black males lived as lodgers in other people's households. The median age of the black community was high; overall it was 28 years old but among black males it was even higher at 31. To put it into context in 1900 the overall median age of the United States was 19.4, of all African Americans in the U.S. it was 19.4, of all New Mexicans it was 21.2.  The median age of Albuquerque African Americans was even higher than the age of all blacks in New Mexico which was high to start with at 26.8. The Census Bureau reminds us that, “The states with a median age far above the average are those in which a large part of the Negroes are immigrants [from other states.]” &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If we group people into four age groups children (&amp;lt;15), young adults (15 to 34), mature adults (35 to 64) and elders (65+) we can see how the Albuquerque African American community differed from the rest of New Mexico in 1900.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pie Chart Age groups" src="/images/Chart2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The percentage of the population who were children is much less in the Albuquerque black population than in the New Mexico population as a whole. Adults both young and mature made up a greater percentage of the Albuquerque African American population than the New Mexico total population and elders comprised less. All of these are demographic signs that the Albuquerque African American population was a community in flux. The low percentage of children and the high percentage of adults suggest that the community's growth was being sustained by in migration rather than natural increase. This was particularly true of the Albuquerque black male population in which these trends were heightened. Among Albuquerque black males the percentage of children is even lower (21.1%) and we note that among adults only 32.5% are young adults while 45.5 % are mature adults and less than 1% are elders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The migration statistics bear out that this was a community formed by in-migration.  Some 79% of African Americans living in New Mexico were born outside the territory as compared to only 22% of the white population.  Only twenty one percent of the territory's African Americans were born in New Mexico while the next highest contributing states were Virginia, Texas and Missouri in that order. In Albuquerque about the same proportion of the population was born in New Mexico (22%) and it was followed by Texas, Missouri and Kentucky. In other words about 78% of Albuquerque African Americans were born elsewhere. This wasn't the same for men and women. A greater proportion of the men migrated into New Mexico. Eighty three percent of the men and only 75% of the women were born outside the territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trend continues through 1920 as a decreasing proportion of Albuquerque African Americans were born in New Mexico. Throughout the period the gap between the percentage of Albuquerque black men and Albuquerque black women born in New Mexico remains about the same. Only after the Depression decade of the 1930's do they approach each other in 1940 at a point below that of 1900. In 1940 after the greatest increase ever in Albuquerque's black population, less than twenty percent of both men and women were born in New Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Line graph Percentage of African Americans Born in NM" src="/images/Chart3.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The early Albuquerque African American community was moreover a community in transit.  Of the 224 people found in the 1900 manuscript census less than 10% were found in the 1910 manuscript census. This is at best only a rough approximation of how many people stayed in Albuquerque; women who stayed may have changed their names through marriage; people may have stayed but moved beyond the city limits.  I have tried to correct for this by including the areas just outside Albuquerque in the manuscript census and trying to discern female holdovers through similar names, birthplaces and parents' birthplaces. One can conclude even from these rough estimates that the great preponderance of the community had moved elsewhere by 1910.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to note the slow evolution to a more settled and less transitory community is to look at home ownership. The manuscript census lists whether the heads of household own or rent their residences. If we examine the figures for the African American heads of household we see some clear trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: center"&gt;1900&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: center"&gt;1910&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: center"&gt;1920&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;HHH&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;66&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;66&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Owned&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(15.2%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(14.3%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(39.4%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Rented&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;52&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(78.8%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(85.7%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;38&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(57.6%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Unknown&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(6.1%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(0.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(3.0%)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that the number of household heads remains about the same between 1900 and 1920. This coordinates with our knowledge that the total African American population of Albuquerque overall did not change much in this period. The major change is in the number of household heads who own rather than rent their residences. Although the percentage of renters remains significantly above 50%, the number and percentage of home owners more than doubles. The movement toward more ownership also translates to a movement of location.  Using the Geographic Information System we can track where African Americans lived in Albuquerque through each manuscript census. We can use the addresses given in the census to map where African American rentals or houses owned would have been located in contemporary Albuquerque.  A map of the 1900 census would showed them in rentals in the central city area.  As homeownership increased however we see them moving out of the central city to the further reaches of the city and beyond. On the map the O's represent houses owned and the R's are rentals. The central city is shown in red and the new areas where most of the African American home owners clustered is in blue. Note the area in blue towards the south because that is where the black residences would cluster in decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albuquerque African Americans themselves may have had a hand in this change.  In 1918 a group of people active in the local black Mount Olive Baptist church formed the Rio Grande National Development Society. The society was formed for the purpose of buying and selling real estate and operating sanitoria for “colored peoples, Mexicans and Indians. The pastor of the Mount Olive Baptist Church, Reverend A. J. Lewis became president of the new society, Kendrick Penman (listed in the census as a blacksmith helper) became vice president and Dr. James Lewis was the secretary.  It had as subsidiary companies the Rio Grande Realty Company and the Booker T. Washington Memorial Sanatorium.  All three operated out of Dr. Lewis's office. The sanatorium itself was located near Dr. Lewis's residence and the greatest growth in black owned residences were in areas where the president of the society lived in the northern light blue section of the map and where the manager of the realty company lived in the southern light blue area. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Map of Where African americans Rented or Bought Homes in 1920" src="/images/Map1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that neither of these areas was exclusively African American.  They were mixed race areas where whites lived alongside people of other races.
Both the AME church and a black Masonic lodge were in operation by the turn of the century. Judging from the names of the deacons and the officers of the lodge the same people were instrumental in both. There was great turnover among these civic leaders of the black community. No more than a third of the church officers, stewards and stewardess listed in the city directories were still in Albuquerque in the next census in 1910. Many of the institutions the community created however, like the African Methodist Episcopal church, remained and were continued by their successors. The institutions that were created and the few families that remained in Albuquerque therefore took on a crucial role in the continuity of the community. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have already seen the census occupations of African Americans are not always reflective of their lives.  Nevertheless they are important in understanding the community. The occupations of Albuquerque African Americans differed a bit from African Americans in other parts of New Mexico as we can see in Table B. In all columns the total number of men in each category is listed in parentheses. The first column lists the most prevalent occupations of New Mexico African American males in 1900.  We can compare it to the next column which lists the most common occupations of Albuquerque African American males in the same year. The third and fourth columns are the most common occupations for black females in New Mexico and Albuquerque respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="table-b-1900-occupations"&gt;Table B 1900 Occupations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;NM Black Males&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Albuquerque Black Males&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;NM Black Females&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Albuquerque Black Females&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Military (216)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Porter (15)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Servants (62)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Laundress (7)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Miners (200)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Day Laborer (12)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Laundresses (35)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Cook (3)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Servants (102)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Teamster (6)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Lodging House Keepers (8)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;House Keepers (3)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Laborers (94)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Barber (6)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;House Keepers (8)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Nurse (1)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Porters (30)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Janitor (6)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Laborers (5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Lodging House Keepers (1)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Barbers (22)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Laborer (6)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nurses/Midwives (5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Herders (20)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Waiter (5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Teamsters (19)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Cook (4)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that there were no black military men nor miners in Albuquerque as there were in other parts of New Mexico. Nor were there many primary good producers like herders, farmers or agricultural laborers. African American men in Albuquerque were confined to service occupations like porter, teamster, janitor, waiter, cook or unspecified laborers. This is not totally unexpected in an urban environment which should concentrate service jobs. For example one quarter of the black barbers and half of the black janitors in New Mexico were in Albuquerque. Unfortunately the census figures from this census do not tell us how many black Albuquerque citizens worked for the railroad. For the women what is striking is how few black Albuquerque women worked outside the home at this time.  Only fifteen listed occupations and none of them were maids working in other people's homes. When they had a choice black women's labor did not enter the work world at this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Methodist Church in 1913" src="/images/MethodistChurch1913.jpg" /&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1912 the territory of New Mexico became a state and the 1920 census is the first to reflect that change. The 1920 manuscript census shows that while the size of the Albuquerque African American community did not increase much, most of the community were newcomers.  These newcomers contained a group of highly educated African Americans who settled in the town from 1909 to 1915 and became the community leaders of the 1920's. They included S. W. Henry a teacher who began to edit an African American newspaper, the Southwest Review in 1924, James Dennis a medical doctor, T.M. Brinson a violinist graduate of Chicago Conservatory of Music and A.L. Mitchell a graduate of Wiley College in Texas. Several of the newcomers were retired Army veterans who had served in the African American 9th and 10th Cavalry or the 24th or 25 infantry. Although a few families did remain from 1910 an abnormal number of those who did stay had been widowed during the intervening ten years. New institutions had been formed such as a branch of the fledgling National Association for the Advancement of Colored People organized in 1913 but chartered in 1915 and an additional African American church, the Mount Olive Baptist Church organized in 1909 although its members had been meeting since 1898 led by Mrs. Tabaytha Watson with her son Green and daughter Anna. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote7"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Mt Olive Baptist Church 1915" src="/images/BaptistChurch1915.jpg" /&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote8"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Third black church, God's House Church, was founded in 1916. It met in the house of its leader evangelist Emma Heil Pettiford and her husband Beverly Pettiford.  It would not get its own church building until 1924.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the church organizations several other self-help organizations were founded during this period.  In 1914 eight women became the charter members of the Home Circle Club which at first was part of the national Colored Women's Clubs but later struck out on its own. It was not only a women's social club it provided training in home economics, college scholarships for black youth and encouragement of black family life. In 1919 the Little Forum was formed with seven child charter members in the words of its founder to “[create an interest in attending high school, to attain and maintain a high standard in our manners and decorum…[and to promote] our social and intellectual advancement.” A.L Mitchell, a former teacher who was prevented from teaching when he moved to Albuquerque because the Albuquerque school system would not hire black teachers, was put in charge of the club. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote9"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A branch of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People was chartered in 1915 just six years after the national NAACP was formed. The NAACP had grown out of the black Albuquerque Independent Society because of discrimination faced in Albuquerque High School and elsewhere in Albuquerque public facilities. In 1907 the first African American girls scheduled to graduate from Albuquerque High School had to graduate from the high school section of the University of New Mexico instead when community members objected to their graduation although they had fulfilled all the requirements. It was not until 1914 that the first African American graduated with her class from Albuquerque High School. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote10"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;   No African American would be allowed to teach in the Albuquerque public schools until the 1950's decades later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such slights did not stop African American parents from sending their children to school. In 1900 almost two thirds of Albuquerque African Americans age 5 to 20 went to school.  This was a higher percentage than New Mexican African Americans as a whole (42.9%) and U.S. born New Mexican whites (41.9%.) In 1910 the rate sank to 54%, less than New Mexican blacks as a whole (55.7%) and New Mexican whites (61.2%.) It recovered in 1920 to a whopping 83.3% surpassing the total of all New Mexican whites (66%) and even other urban blacks (70%.) The manuscript census shows that it was those children age five or six and those over 16 who were most likely not to be in school.  In other words Albuquerque African Americans tended to start school a little later in life and leave a little earlier perhaps because they had to enter the workforce earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rates of illiteracy among Albuquerque African Americans had always been low. In 1900 when the rate of illiteracy for all of New Mexico was 30% the rate among Albuquerque blacks was only 11.4%. This Albuquerque African American illiteracy rate fell to 8.5% in 1910 and 4.8% in 1920. As comparison the rate of illiteracy in the United States and in New Mexico as a whole is provided in Table C as are the school attendance rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="table-c"&gt;Table C&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id="illiteracy-among-those-age-10"&gt;Illiteracy among those age 10+&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;1900&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;1910&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;1920&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Albuquerque Blacks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;11.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;8.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;4.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;All New Mexico&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;30.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;20.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;15.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;United States&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;11.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;7.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;6.0%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id="comparative-school-attendance-age-5-to-20"&gt;Comparative School Attendance age 5 to 20&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;1900&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;1910&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;1920&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Albuquerque Blacks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;65.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;54.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;83.3%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;NM Blacks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;42.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;55.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;45%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;NM Whites&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;41.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;61.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;66%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Urban NM Blacks&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;62.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;70%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Urban NM Whites&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;63.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;68%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already seen that from the beginning of black settlement in Albuquerque African Americans were not just content to accept the roles that the white economy gave them: for example  porters and janitors for the men, domestic service as cooks or maids for the women. In fact the list of occupations in the 1900 census for New Mexico territory is quite extensive ranging from military service, mining, agriculture and masonry to musicians or music teachers. They used those roles as stepping stones to their own entrepreneurial projects as early as the 1880's. The best examination of black entrepreneurship in this early period remains, remarkably, an undergraduate paper written at the University of New Mexico almost 40 years ago by John Joseph Ellis. Ellis makes two key points about this period. First for some people there was an oscillation between the roles in the white economy and black entrepreneurship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Such businesses … usually operated out of the home, were supplements to the family income which allowed a skillful craftsman to use his abilities, under his own terms, in good times.  When times were bad, the business could be put aside and one's labor hired out.  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote11"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all business the primary question was finding a market for your goods or services.  Those business that could serve the entire Albuquerque market are the ones that fared best. In the 1880's and 90's there were black commercial farmers who could sell their produce to the New Albuquerque market. A remnant of this trade can be found after 1900 in a dairy owned and operated by Joseph and Lucinda market lasted all the way to the 1920's. In 1907 William T. Thornton established a carpet and clothes cleaning business which apparently had customers outside of Albuquerque as well. The first black owned restaurant and a black owned saloon popped up in 1908. African Americans owned barber shops, tailoring establishments, shoe making and repair shops, and billiard or pool parlors. They often opened businesses that relied on skills they had developed elsewhere like former cavalry scout George Hutchinson who opened a blacksmith shop next to his home in 1909. When any of these businesses were sold it was often to other African Americans first although many eventually passed into white ownership. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote12"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second key point that Ellis makes is that black businesses could become important as sources of employment in the black community. He notes a sharp contrast between the businesses of the 1880's to 1900's and those of 1912 and beyond:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…before 1912, the ventures were usually small, short-lived, and generally served to supplement the incomes of single individuals and their households….none of the ventures had provided employment for Blacks outside the immediate family, and thereby few Blacks experienced employment and what training in business a full-blown enterprise could offer. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote13"&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He feels that several businesses established after 1912 in contrast “provided jobs, experience and patronage for the black community,” much as other ethnic businesses did. He attributes this ‘sudden burst of activity” to undefined pressures on Blacks in the job market. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote14"&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A prime example of this was the Bryant Messenger Service established by the Bryant brothers General, Heard and Willard.  They emigrated from Texas in 1906 and at first worked as general labors and porters. They had bigger dreams than that and started to open their own businesses. General Bryant opened that first black owned restaurant in 1908 and a grocery store soon after. To supplement his income he worked as a porter in the Commercial Club where white business leaders met, relaxed and presumably made deals or exchanged information. His brother Heard became a partner in a shoemaking venture. In 1912 General and Heard Bryant opened to Bryant Messenger Service which gave employment to blacks as drivers or bicycle and motorcycle messengers as seen below. The company picked up baggage at the train station, carried messages to places without telephone service and delivered to the sanitaria where tuberculosis patients lived who had moved to Albuquerque because of the climate. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote15"&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Bryant Messenger Service" src="/images/MessengerService.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote16"&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast those ventures that relied on a predominantly African American clientele did not do as well. The Albuquerque African American community was too small to form commercially viable enterprises that catered to the community and at the same time too small to have the mainstream economy take its needs into account. There were few black professionals in New Mexico and only a couple in Albuquerque. A black lawyer arrived to set up a practice in 1912 but was gone by 1914. Attempts to found black newspapers and printing shops were usually short-lived. Albuquerque's first black doctor arrived in 1914 and managed to stay afloat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the foundation had been laid by 1920 things had not changed much. As we can see from Table D not much had changed in the size or composition of the male population. The median age is a little older but the number of people in each category is roughly the same.  For women the median age has gone up because there are significantly fewer children and more people have moved into the elder category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="table-d"&gt;Table D&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Composition of Albuquerque Black Population&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Males&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Males&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Females&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Females&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;1900&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;1920&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;1900&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;1920&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Median Age&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Children (14 and under)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;38&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Young Adult (15 to 34)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;41&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Mature Adult (35 to 64)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;57&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Elder (65 and older)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;125&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;129&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;126&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;112&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that had changed was that the black population of Albuquerque was becoming a smaller part of the city.  From 1900 to 1920 Albuquerque's total population had risen from about 6200 to a little over 15,000 while the African American population had basically stayed the same or even dropped a little to a bit over 200. The result was that as a percentage of Albuquerque's population African Americans had dropped from 4% to 1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The occupations open to African Americans in the economy hadn't changed much. Of the black males age fourteen or older 80 or about 78% of them were employed and a third worked for the railroad. Only 28 or about 30% of black women age 14 or older were employed twelve or about 43% were employed in private homes. Table E lists the top occupations for Albuquerque black males and females in 1920:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="table-e"&gt;Table E&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Occupation&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;% Black Males&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Occupation&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;% Black females&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Porter&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;28.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Domestic&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;53.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Laborer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;16.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Cook&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;14.3%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Janitor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;8.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Laundress&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;10.7%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Cook&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;8.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Nurse&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;7.1%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Minister&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;5.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Manicurist&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;3.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Barber&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;5.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Hairdresser&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;3.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Servant&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;3.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Seamstress&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;3.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Farmer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;2.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Stenographer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;3.6%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Physician&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;2.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost 63% of the males were employed as porters, laborers, janitors and cooks. Among black females almost 80% were domestic servants, cooks and laundresses. Interestingly less than a quarter of the males were unemployed by the mainstream economy but over two thirds of the women were able to withhold their labor from the dominant economy and yet get by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So by 1920 the economic parameters had been set, the key social institutions were in place and many of the key actors had arrived. In the next two decades the population was to rise, social prejudices were to increase, and the state of the nation was to intrude on a black community that was simply trying to build a life for itself. The community was to find a voice for itself and its ambitions, but that voice was to fade away.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Before the Twentieth Century</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/before-the-twentieth-century/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/before-the-twentieth-century/</id>
    <published>2015-03-07T15:13:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2015-04-18T14:49:57-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1 id="before-the-twentieth-centurysup1footnote1sup"&gt;Before the Twentieth Century&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to look at African and African American migration in New Mexico is to see it as the unintended consequence of greater events. Human migration has been part of human existence from the beginning. It is characteristically comprised of short movements of individuals or groups up to a small band. Even if the long term effect is to relocate many people it is not like a cattle stampede in which many people move together at the same time unless it is a forced migration.  Forced migrations come about when there are ecological disasters or human intervention in the normal migration patterns.  The slave trade, as an example, forced many people to move according to its dictates from Africa to the Middle East or the Americas. A forced migration like the slave trade had many ancillary and unforeseen effects including miscegenation, freedmen, slave revolts and runaways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Slaves in Africa" src="/images/slavesInAfrica.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These by-products of the slave system were instrumental in the dangerous exploration of new lands by the European slave powers and their surrogates.  Africans and African mestizos were the most expendable and served as the pioneer edge of European exploration into what became the United States Western region. By accepting this role black people were able to avoid the constraints of the slave system and build a modicum of independence for themselves though at a great cost. The outcastes of the slave system became the explorers who dotted the southwest at first under Spanish then Mexican imprimatur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Portrait of Estevanico" src="/images/Estavanico.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example the guide who was the first non-native American to explore the New Mexico region as part of a sixteenth century Spanish expedition was a Moroccan African named Estevan. He scouted for the 1539 Fray Marcos de Niza expedition into Northern New Spain in the Sonora desert. He was also one of the first martyrs of European exploration (probably unwillingly) when he was killed for his efforts by a Native American group. Subsequent sixteenth century expeditions followed Estevan’s route and contained black or mixed race members some of whom deserted to live in what is now New Mexico.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  As Mexican settlers moved into the region in the seventeenth and eighteen centuries, Mexican Afro-mestizos comprised part of the early settler communities in the Southwest. Historian Quintard Taylor quotes Father Estevan de Perea as characterizing most of New Mexico’s non-Native Americans as “mestizos, mulattoes and zambohijos [children of Native American fathers and mestizos, mulattoes or blacks.]” &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Slaves in Repose" src="/images/slavery1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic dictates of the agriculture for which African slaves were needed in the U.S. kept them in the U.S. South. They moved mainly from the Old South of Virginia and the Carolinas to the New South of Mississippi, Alabama, and Louisiana as the slave economy changed and grew. Once the American Civil War literally unshackled them from the slave system the possibility of movement began to take shape. The debt peonage system which succeeded slavery in the South kept most of the slaves in that region. At the time of the country’s founding 91% of the African American population lived in the South.  At the beginning of the Civil War that number was still 92%. While it fell slightly at the end of the war it did not slip below 90% until the turn of the 20th century. The end of slavery did however allow the migration patterns of African Americans to return to a more natural pattern for an intrepid few. The 1880’s and 90’s saw the movement of some African Americans to the Midwest and the west in what was called “The Great Migration.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was minimal, if any, settlement in New Mexico by African Americans during the first half of the nineteenth century. The 1860 census shows only 85 African Americans counted in New Mexico. Another analysis found 53 blacks and 82 mulattoes in that year. Nobody knows how many of these people were slaves but most of slaves came when slave owners, principally army officers, brought their “property” into the territory. New Mexico’s Spanish and Mexican roots had built a supply of peons to provide labor and so African American slavery never became widespread. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote7"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The 1870 federal census lists only 172 African Americans living in New Mexico. That number jumped to over 1,000 in 1880 and almost 2,000 in 1890. Most of that increase were black soldiers who were sent to the West by the government.  They were the so-called “Buffalo soldiers.” Over 200,000 black troops had served in the Union army during the Civil War, about 10% of all troops.  The black units were reorganized in 1869 to become the 9th and 10th cavalry units as well as the 24th and 25th infantry units of the army.  In the last half of the nineteenth century several of these black units were dispatched to the West to protect settlers from Native American raids. Several of these regiments were stationed in New Mexico at times and they made up the majority of African Americans in the territory. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote8"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Placque in Albuquerque Old Town Plaza" src="/images/oldAbqPlacque.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote9"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been black residents in Albuquerque from the beginning. When Old Albuquerque was founded in 1706 five of the twenty-two founding heads of household were black or mulatto. Descendants of the founders and other black and mixed race immigrants have lived in Albuquerque ever since then. A 1750 census of Albuquerque listed 200 Native Americans and 500 others of whom some 50 were “mulattoes”.  A later 1790 census only lists 5 mulattoes which historian Maisha Baton takes as a sign of their absorption into the community rather than their absence from it. Albuquerque remained a small and isolated community throughout the nineteenth century until the advent of the Santa Fe railroad which linked New Mexico to the rest of the country.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote10"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Old Steam Engine" src="/images/railroad.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote11"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Present day Albuquerque was a product of the Atcheson, Topeka and Santa Fe Railroad’s expansion west. The company started in 1868 as a small railroad to link two Kansas towns Atcheson and Topeka but soon turned its attention to expanding westward. By 1872 it had reached Dodge City, Kansas and by 1878 Trinidad, Colorado. In 1879 they made an agreement with two other rail lines to acquire the right away to reach all the way to the Pacific Ocean. Habitually short of capital, when they finally entered the New Mexico territory near Las Vegas, New Mexico, they asked the town for $10,000, a land grant and a free right of way.  When the town did not provide any of these it laid track a mile outside of town in effect bypassing it. They determined that the best route to lay new track was some eighteen miles south of Santa Fe and did so.  Only concessions and a bond issue from the town persuaded the railroad to build a spur line into Santa Fe. As they continued their push into the middle Rio Grande Valley the company first approached the town of Bernalillo.  When a large landowner there offered them land at $425 an acre, they quickly left as they were expecting to pay $2 or $3 per acre. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote12"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus by the time they reached Albuquerque a bit to the south, they had already effectively demonstrated their willingness to bypass towns that didn’t accede to their demands and their desire to lay track in the most advantageous geographical areas for it. Their surveyors determined that the shortest route to lay track was not through Albuquerque itself which was nestled in a bend in the river Rio Grande, but a mile and a half east. A few prominent Albuquerque citizens anxious to have the railroad turned land speculators and bought up the land around the proposed route. They agreed to deed the land to the railroad for $1 an acre in exchange for 50% of the price when the railroad company would later sell it at a greatly inflated price to commercial developers once the railroad came through. In April, 1880 the train reached what would become New Albuquerque with a great celebration to mark its arrival. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote13"&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were only 16 African Americans listed in that first census of New Albuquerque later that summer.  Most of these were listed as cooks and domestics. Only one black family was listed among them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Census" src="/images/census.png" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote14"&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The census listings rarely tell the whole story of black ambitions and accomplishments. One man listed as a “cook” in the 1880 census was the proprietor of a business, the New Mexico Novelty Store, by 1883.  The business lasted until 1896. A retired miller listed in the 1880 census was the proprietor of a rooming house in 1883. There were 3 black children in the Albuquerque schools in 1884 and that number peaked at 34 before the end of the century. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote15"&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="School Children" src="/images/schoolChildren.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote16"&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 1885 the population had grown to the point where we can begin to see the emergence of the social trappings of a community. Historian Bernice Rebord writes that African Americans “had a social life patterned after the town’s.” Two African American women organized an African Drama Club, an African American band performed concerts in front of two of the town’s major hotels and the town’s skating rink was reserved for African Americans on certain days. An African American Methodist mission was organized in 1882 but its first facility was not able to accommodate its congregation. The church at first therefore rented space in other buildings for its weekly services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Colored Methodist Mission" src="/images/methodistMission.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote17"&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was reorganized as the Colored Methodist Mission and the township of Albuquerque donated land for it in 1883. The ladies of the mission held socials probably to raise money to build a church building. They were successful and eventually a new brick building opened in 1892 at Coal Avenue and Third Street in Albuquerque. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote18"&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only scattered clues about what life was like for the burgeoning African American population in Albuquerque before the turn of the twentieth century.  Some of those clues are from photographs from the period. A photograph from 1884 of the first automobile to arrive in Albuquerque shows three nattily dressed black men in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Albuquerue's First Automobile" src="/images/firstAuto.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote19"&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others show African American men at work. We can see one working as the desk clerk for the white businessman’s club in Albuquerque in 1895.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="African American Desk Clerk" src="/images/deskClerk.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote20"&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see another working as a railroad porter sometime during the 1890’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="African American Railroad Porter" src="/images/blackPorter.jpg" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote21"&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are indicative of the occupations available to African Americans at the turn of the century.  Most, particularly the women, could work as domestics for the white population or the men as porters and other employees of the railroad. Although there were a few who could carve out different livelihoods for themselves, these were the two options the white economic system set as lynchpins for the economic life of Albuquerque African Americans as the twentieth century began. As we shall see African Americans tried to surmount these options whenever they could.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
